Inventory of the Akademiia nauk SSSR, Sibirskoe otdeleniie miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Akademiia nauk SSSR, Sibirskoe otdeleniie miscellaneous records
1967-1986
93009
Akademiia nauk SSSR, Sibirskoe otdeleniie.
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates to the administration of scientific and other academic research in Siberia and elsewhere in the Soviet Union, consisting of regulations, directives, resolutions, minutes, decisions, and correspondence.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
N. N. Poppe sound recording, Hoover Institution Archives
Harold Adams Innis typescript: Ottawa to Moscow, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
The Russian Academy of Science was founded in Saint Petersburg by Peter the Great in 1724. The name varied over the years, becoming the Akademiia Nauk SSSR (the USSR Academy of Science) in 1917.
The national academy of the USSR had a network of scientific research institutes across the Soviet Union, with headquarters in Moscow. The Academy was a civil and self-governed, non-commercial organization chartered by the Government of the USSR, consisting of specialized scientific branches.
The Sibirskoe (Siberian Branch) was established in 1950. After the dissolution of the Soviet Union, by decree of the president of Russia on December 2, 1991, the institute once again became Rossiĭskaia akademiia nauk (The Russian Academy of Science), inheriting all facilities of the USSR Academy of Science in the territory of Russia.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to the administration of scientific and other academic research in Siberia (Novosibirsk) and elsewhere in the Soviet Union. It consists of 28 bound volumes of regulations, directives, resolutions, protocols, decisions, and correspondence. It includes regulations of the central office of the Akademiia nauk SSSR, the Gosudarstvennyiĭ komitet SSSR po nauke i tekhnike, and the Gosudarstvennyiĭ komitet SSSR po trudu i sotsial'nym voprosam.
The collection is a source of documents to study the form and content of regulations, the nature of procedures, the style of operation, the sociological nature of Soviet bureaucracy, and the history of activities and scientific policy of the USSR Academy of Science between 1967 and 1986.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Science--Soviet Union.; Research--Soviet Union.; Education--Soviet Union.; Siberia (Russia); Soviet Union. Gosudarstvennyiĭ komitet po nauke i tekhnike.
Collection Contents
- Akademiia nauk SSSR (AN SSSR), Sibirskoe (SO), 1967-1986 (Box 1-2)
  - "Rukovodiashchie dokumenty Prezidiuma AN SSSR i SO AN SSSR po okhrane truda i tekhnike bezopasnosti" (3 vols., nos. 1-3), 1967-1978 (Folder 1: 1-3)
  - "Rasporiazheniia i postanovlennia SO prislannye dlia svedeniia" (1 vol., no. 2), 1977 (Folder 1: 4)
  - "Kopii rasporiazheniĭ i postanovleniĭ SO AN SSSR po tekhnike bezopasnosti" (1 vol.), 1978-1980 (Folder 1: 5)
  - "Postanovleniia I rasporiazheniia SO AN SSSR" (1 vol., no. 2), 1979 (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Perepiska s AN SSSR" (1 vol., no. 103.1), 1980 (Folder 2: 1)
  - "SO AN SSSR: rasporiazheniia" (1 vol., no.1227), 1985 (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Kopii rasporiazheniĭ i postanovleniĭ Prezidiuma SO AN SSSR, prislannye dlia rukovodstva i svedeniia" (2 vols., nos. 1224.2, 1227), 1985 (Folder 2: 3-4)
- Akademiia Nauk SSSR, 1985-1986 (Box 2-3)
  - "Kopii rasporiazheniĭ i postanovleniĭ Prezidiuma AN SSSR, prislannye dlia rukovodstva i svedeniia" (1st of 2 vol., no. 1226), 1985-1986 (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Kopii rasporiazheniĭ i postanovleniĭ Prezidiuma AN SSSR, prislannye dlia rukovodstva i svedeniia" (2nd of 2 vol., no. 1226), 1985-1986 (Folder 3: 1)
  - "Kopii postanovleniĭ AN SSSR otnosiashchiesia k deiatel'nosti biblioteki" (1 vol.), 1986 (Folder 3: 2)
- Gosudarstvennyĭ komitet po trudu i sotsial?nym voprosam (Goskomtrud), 1986 (Box 3)
  - "Kopii postanovleniĭ Goskomtruda" (1 vol., no. 23), 1986 (Folder 3: 3)
- Gosudarstvennyĭ komitet po nauke i tekhnike (GKNT), 1978-1986 (Box 3-4)
  - "Kopii postanovleniĭ GKNT" (4 vols., no. 112), 1978-1981 (Folder 3: 4-5)
  - "Kopii postanovleniĭ, protokolov i vypisok iz protokolov GKNT" (5 vols., no. 1123), 1982-1986 (Folder 4: 1-3)